<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Privacy</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Privacy">
            <p>
                DataNucleus abides by all relevant laws in the area of data security.
            </p>
            <br/>
            <subsection name="Security of Personal Information">
                <p>
                    Any information provided by you through the use of an online form or email will be kept private.
                    This information is essential to process and complete your request.
                    DataNucleus does not sell or otherwise give away your private information to any third party.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The information we collect may be helpful to us in improving this Web site performance and can
                    therefore be used for this purpose. We will not contact you without your express wish to be
                    contacted.
                </p>
                <p>
                    No information will be disclosed by us without your personal permission, excluding cases when
                    it is required by our legal obligations according to the Law. Please also be advised that we
                    have taken all the necessary measures to ensure security of your personal information without
                    any alteration. Any access to the site users' personal information is strictly controlled.
                    We will also take all reasonable measures to ensure that any third parties we transfer data
                    to will provide sufficient protection of your personal information.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Links to third party sites">
                <p>
                    DataNucleus' website may provide links to third party websites.
                    We accept no responsibility for the content or privacy policy of those sites whatsoever.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
