<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Support</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Support : Free and Commercial">
            <p>
                With any software, there are times when you need assistance to make full use of it. Here at DataNucleus
                we want you to make the best of the software that we provide. For that reason we provide both
                commercial and free support facilities.
            </p>
            <subsection name="Commercial Support">
                <p>
                    Where you or your company require timely support when you need it without having to wait for
                    somebody to respond on a forum we provide commercial support. You could, for example, have a
                    preference for email support, or maybe phone support. If this is the case then we can discuss
                    what would be possible. Please refer to 
                    <a href="../services/index.html#support">our Support services</a> for details.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Free Support">
                <p>
                    DataNucleus provides its own <a href="http://forum.datanucleus.org">online forums</a>
                    providing a place to discuss issues you are having. We don't guarantee to provide answers on this
                    forum. It is simply a place where you could get some level of support when people have time.
                    This may not be adequate for some people hence why we provide the commercial version above.
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Check the Documentation for 
                        <a href="../products/accessplatform/index.html">DataNucleus Access Platform</a> before 
                        anything else. The answer is usually there, either in a tutorial/example, or in one of 
                        the many guides.</li>
                    <li>Look in the <a href="../products/accessplatform/logging.html">DataNucleus Log</a>. 
                        This usually contains a lot of information that may answer the issue. 
                        You can always configure the log to give more output.</li>
                    <li>Try a recent build to see if your version is out of date and the expected result is achieved 
                        with the latest nightly builds.</li>
                    <li>Go to the <a href="http://forum.datanucleus.org" target="_blank">Online Forum</a> and ask. 
                        Always try to give as clear a description of the problem as possible, together with your input 
                        data, and any associated log output.
                        <b>Please be aware that we have very little time for this type of support and 
                        contributors to DataNucleus are more likely to get any available free support</b></li>
                </ol>
                <p>
                    <i>Please note that due to attempts by spammers to post links as well as attempts by 
                        some internet domains to flood the DataNucleus Forum it has been necessary to block
                        particular IP addresses. If you find yourself on one of these IP addresses then you need
                        to consider how your IP address has been used in this way, and that it means you will not
                        have access to this free resource. Apologies for the inconvenience if that is the case
                        but its a free forum and we don't have time to tolerate such nonsense.</i>
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>