<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Support and Services</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Free Support">
            <a name="free"/>
            <p>
                With any software, there are times when you need assistance to make full use of it. Here at DataNucleus
                we want you to make the best of the software that we provide. For that reason we provide both
                commercial and free support facilities.
                DataNucleus provides its own <a href="http://forum.datanucleus.org">online forums</a>
                providing a place for you to discuss issues you are having. We don't guarantee to provide answers on this
                forum. It is simply a place where you could get some level of support when people have time.
                This may not be adequate for some people hence why we provide the commercial version below.
            </p>
            <ol>
                <li>Check the Documentation for <a href="products/accessplatform/index.html">DataNucleus Access Platform</a> before 
                    anything else. The answer is usually there, either in a tutorial/example, or in one of the many guides.</li>
                <li>Look in the <a href="products/accessplatform/logging.html">DataNucleus Log</a>. 
                    This usually contains a lot of information that may answer the issue. You can always configure the log to give more output.</li>
                <li>Try a recent build to see if your version is out of date and the expected result is achieved 
                    with the latest nightly builds.</li>
                <li>Go to the <a href="http://forum.datanucleus.org" target="_blank">Online Forum</a> and ask. 
                    Always try to give as clear a description of the problem as possible, together with your input 
                    data, and any associated log output.
                    <b>Please be aware that we have very little time for this type of support and 
                    contributors to DataNucleus are more likely to get any available free support</b></li>
            </ol>
            <br/>
        </section>

        <section name="DataNucleus Commercial Services">
            <a name="commercial"/>
            <img src="images/logos/DataNucleus16-300.jpg" border="0" alt=""/>
            <p>
                DataNucleus is open source software, also providing good documentation and (public) test cases. As a result
                your team could, in principle, train themselves up on the software using the documentation and tests as basis,
                then when they come across problems look through the code and debug problems and/or develop new features. 
                Often though you don't have the time to devote to such activities so would prefer to out source this aspect of 
                your project. We provide for such situations and, since we wrote the software in the first place, nobody is better
                equipped to explain how to use things and/or resolve your problems and get your project moving forward.
                Note that we are the only company offering support for DataNucleus software, and we are the only company with
                committers on this project, and our services are provided at very reasonable prices. 
                <b>You cannot get better value and a higher level of DataNucleus experience than from us.</b>
                Our various commercial services are defined below complete with pricing (<i>note that all prices are in UK pounds (GBP) symbolised by the £ symbol</i>)
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li><b><a href="#onsite_consulting">On-Site Consulting</a></b> : DataNucleus consultant(s) come to your site
                and explain first hand how to resolve the problems you are encountering and/or what is the best practice.</li>
                <li><b><a href="#timebased_consulting">Time-Based Consulting</a></b> : DataNucleus consultant(s) are available online
                at a mutually convenient time to provide answers to your questions via Skype/IRC/IM/phone/etc. Simply pay
                by the hour as and when needed</li>
                <li><b><a href="#support">Support</a></b> : DataNucleus consultant(s) are available to respond to problems
                that come up with your deployments, providing workarounds to your problems, or providing rapid fixes. Optionally
                also allowing for feature additions to meet your requirements</li>
                <li><b><a href="#training">Training</a></b> : DataNucleus consultant(s) can visit your site and provide a training
                appointment to suit your needs. <i>Subject to availability</i></li>
            </ul>

            <a name="onsite_consulting"/>
            <subsection name="On-Site Consulting">
                <p>
                    We deliver on-site engagements to help organisations in achieving 
                    high availability and reliability requirements. This also enables a kick-start for projects thus 
                    reducing the learning curve for customer staff, and minimizing the risk of project failures. 
                    Additionally, engagements can be conducted to deliver proof of concepts with very short schedules.
                </p>
                <p>
                    DataNucleus experts apply their experience and best practices while working with 
                    customer staff to assess the environment, architecture, design and operational 
                    procedures. As an outcome of the engagement, the DataNucleus experts can deliver a 
                    detailed report over the findings, including gaps in architecture, design, 
                    recommendations to address potential problems. During the engagement the customer 
                    staff will likely become more skilled in the data access architectures in general, and 
                    in the DataNucleus product in particular.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <b>Cost</b> : For a European client £900 for a single day, £1750 for 2 days. Reductions for subsequent days. 
                    For clients in the rest of the world please <a href="mailto:consulting@datanucleus.com">Contact Us</a> for details. 
                    Customers are expected to pay for travel/accommodation expenses in order to fulfil such commitments on their site.
                    On-site consulting is not currently available in the USA.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="timebased_consulting"/>
            <subsection name="Time-based Consulting">
                <p>
                    <b>DataNucleus</b> also provides remote consulting using Email/IRC/IM/Skype to provide
                    you with the response when you need it to tackle the issues impacting on your project.
                    This type of support is where questions come up during your deployment of DataNucleus
                    and you need to ask questions for particular situations. You can pay by the hour as and when
                    you need it, when a consultant is available.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <b>Cost</b> : 5 hours = £250, 10 hours = £440, 20 hours = £800.
                    Purchase of larger number of hours also available.
                    <a href="mailto:consulting@datanucleus.com">Contact Us</a> for details
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <a name="support"/>
            <subsection name="Support">
                <p>
                    DataNucleus can provide a level of support to meet your requirements, and rather than having
                    fixed off-the-shelf arrangements we prefer to tailor them to your needs. Below we outline some
                    typical options that could suit your needs. 
                    <a href="mailto:support@datanucleus.com">Contact Us</a> for details.
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><i>General Support</i> for the most common issues on API usage, defect reporting and bug 
                        fixing. It's available for free and on availability on our online forums though
                        has absolutely no guarantee of availability. If you want to receive support when
                        it is needed, then consider the options below</li>
                    <li><i>Incident Support</i> for dedicated support for a single incident.</li>
                    <li><i>Bronze/Gold Support</i> for dedicate support covering multiple incidents over an extended
                        period.</li>
                </ul>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Feature</th>
                        <th width="120">General<br/>Support</th>
                        <th width="120">Incident<br/>Support</th>
                        <th width="120">Bronze<br/>Support</th>
                        <th width="120">Gold<br/>Support</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Software supported</td>
                        <td><a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/products/accessplatform">AccessPlatform</a></td>
                        <td><a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/products/accessplatform">AccessPlatform</a></td>
                        <td><a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/products/accessplatform">AccessPlatform</a></td>
                        <td><a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/products/accessplatform">AccessPlatform</a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Support via Public Forum</td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Support via Email</td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Support via Phone</td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Usage Support</td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Design Support</td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_warning_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Priority Bug Fix</td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>New Feature Support</td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_error_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                        <td><img src="../images/icon_success_sml.gif" border="0" alt=""/></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Languages</td>
                        <td>English</td>
                        <td>English, Spanish</td>
                        <td>English, Spanish</td>
                        <td>English, Spanish</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Support Days</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Mon-Fri</td>
                        <td>Mon-Fri</td>
                        <td>Mon-Fri</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Max Response Time</td>
                        <td>No limit</td>
                        <td>3 days</td>
                        <td>2 days</td>
                        <td>2 days</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Number of incidents</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>1</td>
                        <td>4</td>
                        <td>8</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Support validity</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>1 month</td>
                        <td>6 months</td>
                        <td>1 year</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>Price (without tax)</td>
                        <td>Free</td>
                        <td>£300</td>
                        <td>£1050 [1]</td>
                        <td>£2000 [2]</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                <ul>
                    <li>[1] subsequent incidents charged at £230 each</li>
                    <li>[2] subsequent incidents charged at £210 each</li>
                </ul>
                <p><b>Note that all amounts are specified in GBP (symbolised by the £ symbol)</b></p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="training"/>
            <subsection name="DataNucleus Training">
                <p>
                    <b>DataNucleus</b> can provide on-site training focussing on the needs of customers staff.
                    The backbone of DataNucleus training consists of:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Architectural Persistence Concepts</li>
                    <li>Persistence API choice</li>
                    <li>Object-Relational Mapping</li>
                    <li>Best practices, scalability, performance tuning and capacity planning</li>
                    <li>Administering and monitoring DataNucleus-based applications</li>
                    <li>Testing, debugging and troubleshooting</li>
                    <li>Process Lifecycle : project planning, design and implementation</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    <b>Cost</b> : Please <a href="mailto:support@datanucleus.com">Contact Us</a> for details.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <b>Conditions</b>
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>There is no guarantee of service availability.
                        Training would only be available in a location convenient for ourselves, such as Europe.
                        Training is not currently available in the USA.</li>
                    <li>DataNucleus experts are English, and Spanish speakers, however training material
                        is only written in the English language.</li>
                    <li>Customers must provide the resources necessary and in a timely manner to enable the DataNucleus expert(s) 
                        to perform the engagement.</li>
                </ul>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <a name="customers"/>
            <subsection name="Customers">
                <p>
                    We have many clients to whom we have provided services. Below are a small subset.
                </p>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://www.nightlabs.com" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/nightlabs.png" border="0" alt="Nightlabs"/></a></td>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://www.metamicro.com" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/metamicro.jpg" border="0" alt="Metamicro"/></a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td bgcolor="#36526c"><a href="http://www.bmc.com" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/bmc.gif" border="0" alt="BMC"/></a></td>
                        <td><a href="http://www.transcore.com" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/transcore.png" border="0" alt="Transcore"/></a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://www.yahoo.com" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/yahoo.gif" border="0" alt="Yahoo"/></a></td>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://www.w4global.com" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/w4.png" border="0" alt="W4"/></a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://ge.geglobalresearch.com/" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/ge.png" border="0" alt="General Electric"/></a></td>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://www.lockheedmartin.com/" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/lockheed.png" border="0" alt="Lockheed Martin"/></a></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://www.seismicexchange.com/" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/seismicexchange.gif" border="0" alt="Seismic Exchange"/></a></td>
                        <td width="50%"><a href="http://www.livestream.com/" target="_blank">
                            <img src="images/companies/livestream.jpg" border="0" alt="LiveStream"/></a></td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>