<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Consulting</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Consulting">
            <p>
                DataNucleus is Open Source software. It is provided by a focussed team of highly 
                experienced individuals to perform complex operations.
                While a company could deploy personnel to understand and extend DataNucleus themselves, 
                it is often best to consult the experts in that software to maximise the benefits of its use.
            </p>
            <p>
                These are detailed below.
                <a href="mailto:support@datanucleus.com">Contact Us</a> for details.
            </p>
            <br/>

            <subsection name="On-Site">
                <p>
                    <b>DataNucleus</b> delivers on-site engagements to help organisations in achieving 
                    high availability and reliability requirements. DataNucleus consulting also enables a
                    kick-start for projects thus reducing the learning curve for customer staff, and
                    minimizing the risk of project failures. Additionally, engagements can be conducted to 
                    deliver proof of concepts with very short schedules.
                </p>
                <p>
                    DataNucleus experts apply their experience and best practices while working with 
                    customer staff to assess the environment, architecture, design and operational 
                    procedures. As an outcome of the engagement, the DataNucleus experts can deliver a 
                    detailed report over the findings, including gaps in architecture, design, 
                    recommendations to address potential problems. During the engagement the customer 
                    staff will likely become more skilled in the data access architectures in general, and 
                    in the DataNucleus product in particular.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <b>Cost</b> : For a European client £900 for a single day, £1750 for 2 days.
                    Reductions for subsequent days. For clients in the rest of the world please 
                    <a href="mailto:consulting@datanucleus.com">Contact Us</a> for details. Customers are
                    expected to pay for travel expenses in order to fulfil such commitments on their site.
                    On-site consulting is not currently available in the USA.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Time-based">
                <p>
                    <b>DataNucleus</b> also provides remote consulting using Email/IRC/IM/Skype to provide
                    you with the response when you need it to tackle the issues impacting on your project.
                    This type of support is where questions come up during your deployment of DataNucleus
                    and you need to ask questions for particular situations.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <b>Cost</b> : 5 hours = £250, 10 hours = £440, 20 hours = £800.
                    Purchase of larger number of hours also available.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Consulting Conditions">
                <ul>
                    <li>There is no guarantee of service availability.</li>
                    <li>DataNucleus experts are English and Spanish speakers, however 
                        deliverable reports are only written in the English language.</li>
                    <li>Customers must provide the resources necessary and in a timely manner to enable the 
                        DataNucleus expert(s) to perform the engagement.</li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>

            <p><b>Note that all amounts are specified in GBP (symbolised by the £ symbol)</b></p>
            <br/>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>