<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>Source Code Repository</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Source Code Repository">
            <img src="../images/github.png" alt="GitHub" border="0"/>
            <p>
                DataNucleus source code is hosted on <a href="https://github.com/datanucleus">GitHub</a> and uses
                the <a href="http://git-scm.com//">Git</a> source code version control system.
                You can check out from GitHub using
            </p>
<source>
Using SSH:
git clone git@github.com:datanucleus/{repository-name}.git

Using HTTPS:
git clone https://github.com/datanucleus/{repository-name}.git
</source>
            <p>
                Obviously, not everyone will want to check out all DataNucleus project repositories, so use this command
                for the particular repositories that you require. Note that GitHub repositories are all browsable via
                the web, for example <a href="https://github.com/datanucleus/datanucleus-neo4j">the DataNucleus Neo4j datastore plugin</a>.
                Note that all plugin repositories are <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven projects</a> so you need to
                understand how to build with Maven to build these plugins.
                The DataNucleus repositories present over on GitHub include the following
            </p>
<pre>
datanucleus-core

APIs :
datanucleus-api-jdo
datanucleus-api-jpa
datanucleus-api-rest

Datastores :
datanucleus-excel
datanucleus-hbase
datanucleus-json
datanucleus-ldap
datanucleus-mongodb
datanucleus-neo4j
datanucleus-neodatis
datanucleus-odf
datanucleus-rdbms
datanucleus-xml

Type support :
datanucleus-geospatial
datanucleus-guava
datanucleus-jodatime

Others :
datanucleus-cache
datanucleus-jdo-query
datanucleus-jdo-connector
datanucleus-jpa-query
</pre>
            <p>
                <b>Note that (previous) source code for all versions up to and including 3.3.5 is stored in <a href="scr_sourceforge.html">SourceForge</a>.</b>
            </p>
            <br/>

            <subsection name="Plugins">
                <p>
                    Within the DataNucleus project over on GitHub you have various repositories providing actual DataNucleus plugins.
                    These are currently
                </p>
<pre>
datanucleus-core

APIs :
datanucleus-api-jdo
datanucleus-api-jpa
datanucleus-api-rest

Datastores :
datanucleus-excel
datanucleus-hbase
datanucleus-json
datanucleus-ldap
datanucleus-mongodb
datanucleus-neo4j
datanucleus-neodatis
datanucleus-odf
datanucleus-rdbms
datanucleus-xml

Type support :
datanucleus-geospatial
datanucleus-guava
datanucleus-jodatime

Others :
datanucleus-cache
datanucleus-jdo-query
datanucleus-jdo-connector
datanucleus-jpa-query
</pre>
                <p>
                    All plugins are independently versioned ("master" is the latest branch). This is because they have their own lifecycle, and plugins are
                    bundled together into the "products" (e.g AccessPlatform). So we could have AccessPlatform version 1.1 using version X of a plugin, and 
                    AccessPlatform version 1.2 using version Y of that plugin because it needs some new functionality.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Tests">
                <p>
                    In order to test DataNucleus capabilities we have many end-to-end tests. In the GitHub DataNucleus project these are available
                    in the repository <b>datanucleus-tests</b>. Below that you have some framework projects that need building first, then there are
                    tests split by the persistence API they are for (JDO, JPA, REST, etc).
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Tools">
                <p>
                    The GitHub DataNucleus project also provides some tools to help in using DataNucleus. The repositories providing tools are
                </p>
<pre><![CDATA[
datanucleus-maven-plugin
]]></pre>
                <p>
                    Like with all plugins, the tools are independently versioned since they have their own lifecycle.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Documentation">
                <p>
                    The GitHub DataNucleus project also provides the documentation for DataNucleus. The repositories providing documentation are
                </p>
<pre><![CDATA[
docs-datanucleus
docs-datanucleus-skin
docs-accessplatform
docs-accessplatform-skin
]]></pre>
                <p>
                    The "skin" repositories provide a themed-layour for use with the Maven "site" plugin for each of the documentation sites.
                    Then we have one repository providing the <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org">datanucleus.org</a> website, and one
                    repository providing the <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/products/accessplatform/">AccessPlatform</a> website.
                </p>
                <br/>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>