<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Launch">
            <p>
                <b>April 26th 2008</b>- DataNucleus is launched as the successor for
                <i>Java Persistent Objects (JPOX)</i>. Since its inception in 2003 JPOX has gathered
                a loyal following as a Java persistence solution, initially implementing the JDO1
                specification and then later the JDO2, JDO2.1 and JPA1 specifications. It was designed
                from the outset to be flexible and be standards compliant.
            </p>
            <p>
                DataNucleus will be providing a series of products centred around the data management
                domain within Java applications. The baseline product is <b>DataNucleus Access Platform</b>
                providing persistence using JDO or JPA APIs to RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, Excel and XML datastores.
                It allows use of JDO and JPA XML/annotations with either JDO or JPA API (interchangeably)
                to any of its supported datastores, and allowing querying using JDOQL (JDO API),
                JPQL (JDO/JPA APIs), SQL (JDO/JPA APIs), and db4o Native (JDO API). It will be continually
                extended to provide a wider range of datastore support, together with improved and more
                flexible querying, supporting all pertinent standards in the data persistence domain.
            </p>
            <p>
                DataNucleus is available to provide consulting, training and support for all
                DataNucleus products, delivering unparalleled experience with this software.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
