<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 3.0 M5 Released">
            <p>
                <b>June 14th 2011</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 3.0 ("Newton") Milestone 5 is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including relational, web-based, map-based, and documents.
                <i>Version 3.0 Milestone 5</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Add support for custom class-level and field-level annotations.</li>
				<li>Add support for "native" value generator when field of different type to expected (String &lt;-&gt; long)</li>
				<li>Fix to in-memory query evaluation of String.substring to cater for IndexOutOfBounds</li>
				<li>Support for typing of variables in JDO Typesafe queries</li>
				<li>Fix to not call "fetch" when persisting a new object under some situations</li>
				<li>Support for persistence of Calendar as a String (where required by the datastore)</li>
				<li>Provision of query extensions static final Strings for easier refactoring</li>
				<li>Support for query extensions that are boolean to be specified as that type rather than String</li>
				<li>Enhancer : allow user plugin bundles</li>
				<li>JPA : Support for dynamic generation of "persistence-unit"</li>
				<li>JPA : fix for use of Enum without jdbcType</li>
				<li>RDBMS : fix to possible lockup due to internal map usage for schema</li>
				<li>RDBMS : Enable BINARY/VARBINARY support for MySQL</li>
				<li>RDBMS : Support for max/min of temporal expressions in queries</li>
				<li>RDBMS : fix to case of subquery that was not precompilable so mark the outer query as not precompilable too</li>
				<li>RDBMS : fix to Oracle when using DISTINCT to not select BLOB/CLOB columns</li>
				<li>RDBMS : Migrate to BoneCP 0.7+</li>
				<li>RDBMS : Support detection of timeout exceptions in JDOQL</li>
				<li>RDBMS : Fix to some situations of "complete-table" inheritance strategy usage</li>
				<li>ODF : Support persist of byte[] fields</li>
				<li>ODF : Support for "increment"/"table" value generator</li>
				<li>ODF : fix to retrieval of map field</li>
				<li>Excel : fix to ordering of inserts so we don't overwrite rows/columns</li>
				<li>Excel : fix to retrieve of map field</li>
				<li>Excel : Support for "increment"/"table" value generator</li>
				<li>Excel : Support persist of byte[] fields</li>
				<li>HBase : Cache datastore-query compilation</li>
				<li>HBase : Fix to "hbase" dependency maven groupId</li>
				<li>HBase : Support for persistence of non-serialised map fields</li>
				<li>HBase : Support use of embedded field references in queries in-datastore</li>
				<li>HBase : Support for simple parameter values in queries in-datastore</li>
				<li>MongoDB : fix to "increment" value generator</li>
				<li>MongoDB : fix to exceptions thrown on MongoDB problems to match JDO/JPA specs</li>
				<li>MongoDB : Fix to use of specified datastore name</li>
				<li>MongoDB : Support for schema validation with SchemaTool</li>
				<li>MongoDB : Support for persistence of Date/Calendar as Date (rather than String)</li>
				<li>MongoDB : Support for persistence of maps with Enums keys/values</li>
				<li>MongoDB : Fix to persist of array field</li>
				<li>MongoDB : Cache datastore-query compilation</li>
				<li>IDEA : inclusion of plugin for IDEA, previously developed as separate project (downloadable from Intellij also)</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/project/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>