<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 1.1.1 Released">
            <p>
                <b>Mar 17th 2009</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 1.1.1 ("Rutherford") is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, and Excel.
                <i>Version 1.1.1</i> includes the following changes over 1.1.0
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Added support for generic compilation of long form of Math.XXX, JDOHelper.XXX</li>
                <li>Added support for parameter.method, parameter.field syntaxis in generic queries</li>
                <li>Improved in-memory evaluation of queries to skip candidates that fail sub-expressions
                    due to impossible conditions (unimplemented features, or casts etc)</li>
                <li>Bug fix to always put objects in the L2 cache after a query</li>
                <li>Bug fix to class loading when user has supplied their own loader</li>
                <li>Bug fix to JTA with JCA in afterCompletion (Guido Anzuoni)</li>
                <li>Bug fix to execution of generically compiled queries with parameters so that subsequent
                    invocations use the new parameter values</li>
                <li>Bug fix to runtime enhancement and use of @Extension with JPA to avoid ClassCastException</li>
                <li>Improvements to ordered lists to handle some operations that require indexed positions</li>
                <li>Improvement to object-value-generator to cache the generators</li>
                <li>Bug fix to JPA @Basic annotation allowing for tagging of custom type fields as persistent</li>
                <li>RDBMS "JDOQL2" : Improved support for various String methods</li>
                <li>RDBMS "JDOQL2" : Add support for Math.XXX, JDOHelper.XXX</li>
                <li>RDBMS "JDOQL2" : Support for static class fields</li>
                <li>RDBMS "JDOQL2" : Support chained method invocations</li>
                <li>RDBMS "JDOQL2" : Bug fix to use of parameters when the statement involves unions</li>
                <li>RDBMS "JDOQL2" : Support for input Extent</li>
                <li>RDBMS "JDOQL2" : Support for enums</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Rewrite all backing store "iterator" statements to use new SQL API</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Separate all native (SQL) statements into their own log category</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
