<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 2.1 M3 Released">
            <p>
                <b>May 21st 2010</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 2.1 ("Thomson") Milestone 3 is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, and Excel.
                <i>Version 2.1 Milestone 3</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Change some Maven dependencies to allow use with JDO3</li>
                <li>Fix to generic compilation for "param.field" and use of subquery candidate</li>
                <li>Extend in-memory query evaluation result clause handler to allow variable expression and more</li>
                <li>Fix to in-memory query evaluation for String.matches when the string is null</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to cascade delete on 1-1 when there is a FK present (so leave to datastore)</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to Derby syntax for CROSS JOIN pre-10.6</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to Derby usage with JDOQL2 to restrict use of CLOB/BLOC with DISTINCT/UNION</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Add ability to query in datastore when candidate collection being input</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to Map.containsKey/containsValue to allow for contained variable already having
                    a table in the statement</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to use of subqueries with parameters linking back to the main query</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to use of input positional parameters when one is used multiple times in the 
                    statement</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fetching optimisation when fetching a field and taking the opportunity to load
                    any other non-relation or 1-1/N-1 unloaded fields</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to SQL table namers to allow for multiple levels of subquery</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to Collection.contains(Enum)</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to use of parameter with null value in comparisons</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to use of explicit parameters in subquery</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to generation of "count" query to get size so it takes into account 
                    DISTINCT in the main query</li>
                <li>Excel : Support for persistence of primitive wrapper types</li>
                <li>Excel : Support for persistence of embedded PC fields (Guido)</li>
                <li>Spatial : Added support for all Oracle/PostGIS/MySQL specific methods</li>
                <li>Spatial : Fix to handling of user object in Jts objects when querying</li>
                <li>Spatial : Addition of remaining methods for querying</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/project/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>