<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 2.2 M2 Released">
            <p>
                <b>October 20th 2010</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 2.2 ("Geiger") Milestone 2 is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, and Excel.
                <i>Version 2.2 Milestone 2</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Complete support for JDO3.1 column positioning</li>
                <li>Improved merge of metadata information when sequence or cascade info specified in annotations</li>
                <li>Ability to retain the datastore connection for non-transactional operations</li>
                <li>Fix to a few concurrency bugs around commit/rollback and read/write of objects fields</li>
                <li>Ability to specify a separate connection pool for non-transactional connections</li>
                <li>JDOQL : Allow use of method invocation in grouping statements</li>
                <li>Upgrade to NucleusJDOHelper dirty/loaded methods</li>
                <li>Fix clean up of dynamic fetch groups when closing query/extent/pm</li>
                <li>Fix to metadata requirement for map with embedded key/value so &lt;embedded&gt; is not needed
                    when the key/value is marked as embedded-only</li>
                <li>Fix to PMF startup process so that persistence properties are registered before enablement
                    of some services</li>
                <li>Fix to output from pm.getObjectsById(emptyCollection);</li>
                <li>Improve type handling/comparison capabilities of in-memory query evaluator.</li>
                <li>Basic support for JDO3.1 sequence allocation size and initial value</li>
                <li>getObjectById/find : Ability to not validate objects obtained from L2 cache</li>
                <li>RDBMS : change handling of range when not possible in datastore, now handled in the query result
                    rather than loading all rows into memory first.</li>
                <li>RDBMS : re-enable connection provider plugin point (failover)</li>
                <li>RDBMS : several minor changes to types available for IBM DB2</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to validation of candidate keys, that prevented creation of some unique keys under
                    some circumstances</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to List.get() when used in result clause of JDOQL query</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to maps of embedded keys/values where key part of value (or vice-versa)</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to retrieval of existing indices on Oracle for some table names</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to SQL queries in a J2EE environment</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to order of creation of tables with SchemaTool</li>
                <li>RDBMS : some fixes to use of "allowNulls" on collections/arrays - typo</li>
                <li>JPA : fix to case where sequence name not set</li>
                <li>JPA : fix to EM.getReference to not validate the object</li>
                <li>JPA : fix to use of @Enumerated with @Column</li>
                <li>Enhancer : fix to runtime enhancement, class loading problem</li>
                <li>Enhancer : fix to error message of override of invalid field</li>
                <li>Cache : add option to allow retention of cached objects after close of PMF/EMF, for the case
                    where used by other instances</li>
                <li>LDAP : Remove dependency to "shared-ldap"</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>