<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 3.2 M1 Released">
            <div id="dzone_vote_widget" style="float: left; margin-right: 8px;">
                <script type="text/javascript">var dzone_title = 'DataNucleus Access Platform 3.2 M1 Released';</script>
                <script type="text/javascript">var dzone_url = 'http://www.datanucleus.org/news/access_platform_3_2_m1.html';</script>
		        <script type="text/javascript" language="javascript" src="http://widgets.dzone.com/widgets/zoneit.js"></script>
            </div>
            <p>
                <b>November 24th 2012</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 3.2 ("Copernicus") Milestone 1 is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including relational, web-based, map-based, and documents.
                <i>Version 3.2 Milestone 1</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>OSGi : add version restrictions on many ImportPackage specifications to allow much improved
                    deployability out-of-the-box.</li>
                <li>Merge bytecode enhancer into <i>datanucleus-core</i></li>
                <li>Add option to enhance all classes in a directory and below</li>
                <li>Clean up connection management so that when using Data Federation pooling is based on the
                    ExecutionContext+Datastore and otherwise for the ExecutionContext</li>
                <li>Attach/Detach : add logging of fields being attached/detached</li>
                <li>L2 Cache : enable caching of embedded/serialised fields by default</li>
                <li>L2 Cache : revised process for updating an object in the L2 cache to avoid concurrency</li>
                <li>Clean up ExecutionContext/ObjectProvider contract, to allow for easier addition of alternate
                    StateManagers for different use-cases.</li>
                <li>Change all basic types to be default persistent (so the user doesn't need to explicitly mark them
                    as such), and update several to also be in the DFG</li>
                <li>Change LinkedHashMap support to allow null values</li>
                <li>Significant refactoring of internal DataNucleus classes (see 
                    <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/documentation/plugin_migration.html">this guide</a></li>
                <li>JPA : Update enhancement contract to throw IllegalXXXException instead of JDOXXXException when
                    some error condition occurs, for less JDO impact on JPA usage</li>
                <li>JPA : various fixes to Criteria Query conversion to JPQL</li>
                <li>JPA : add property to cater for J2EE servers that don't respect JPA spec 3.11 EM.close contract</li>
                <li>Neo4j : rewrite connection code to allow multithreaded, and use single connection per PM/EM</li>
                <li>MongoDB : rewrite connection code to use single connection per PM/EM</li>
                <li>MongoDB : use same connection for schema checks as for PM/EM</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Allow SQL "CREATE" statements to be invoked</li>
                <li>RDBMS : add lazy initialisation of secondary datasource (where possible)</li>
                <li>RDBMS : clean up delete handling for some situations</li>
                <li>RDBMS : add support for specifying indexes on map join tables</li>
                <li>XML : clean up connection handling</li>
                <li>Excel : clean up connection handling</li>
                <li>ODF : clean up connection handling</li>
                <li>LDAP : clean up connection handling</li>
                <li>Spatial : add fix to bboxTest method for PostGIS</li>
                <li>Various minor bug fixes and improvements</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>