<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 1.0 M3 Released">
            <p>
                <b>July 6th 2008</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 1.0 ("Faraday") Milestone 3 is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, Excel, NeoDatis ODB, and JSON.
                <i>Version 1.0 Milestone 3</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Rewritten Level 2 caching, allowing full control over which classes are cached
                    and which fields of which classes are cached. Fixed bugs relating to deleted objects
                    previously being cached, and caching of SCO fields</li>
                <li>Rewritten JPQL compiler for use by all datastores.</li>
                <li>Addition of an in-memory JPQL evaluator, supporting basic JPQL syntax so far.</li>
                <li>Support for JDO2.2 "ReadOnly"</li>
                <li>Change in-memory evaluation of JDOQL/JPQL queries to allow evaluation of specific
                    components of the query (rather than the whole query)</li>
                <li>Support for in-memory JDOQL/JPQL evaluation of "/", "%", "&lt;", "&gt;", 
                    "&lt;=", "&gt;=", etc</li>
                <li>Support for in-memory JDOQL evaluation of all common methods (String.matches,
                    String.toUpperCase, etc)</li>
                <li>Bug fix to List.remove(int) when using optimistic transaction</li>
                <li>Bug fix to in-memory JDOQL evaluation of grouping/result clauses</li>
                <li>Support for JPQL querying of db4o datastores</li>
                <li>Support for JPQL querying of NeoDatis ODB datastores</li>
                <li>Support for JPQL querying of XML documents</li>
                <li>Support for JPQL querying of Excel documents</li>
                <li>Support for JPQL querying of LDAP datastores</li>
                <li>Support for JPQL querying of JSON datastores</li>
                <li>Removed original JDOQL querying for db4o - now replaced by generic process, with inbuilt
                    support for more JDOQL syntax.</li>
                <li>Support for persistence of wider range of Object types to Excel datastores, using new
                    generic "String-based" persistence</li>
                <li>Optimisation of location of an object in Excel datastores resulting in reduced 
                    object instantiation</li>
                <li>Support for connection-pooling of LDAP connections (contrib Stefan Seelmann)</li>
                <li>Support for JDOQL querying of NeoDatis ODB datastores</li>
                <li>Support for multiple levels of "xpath" on XML datastores</li>
                <li>Bug fix to GROUP BY on RDBMS datastores when the query has multiple components of a UNION</li>
                <li>Bug fix on RDBMS datastores to re-enable creation of constraints</li>
                <li>Bug fix on RDBMS datastores when using subclass-table inheritance and single subclass</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
