<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 2.0 M1 Released">
            <p>
                <b>July 30th 2009</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 2.0 ("Bohr") Milestone 1 is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, and Excel.
                <i>Version 2.0 Milestone 1</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Addition of plugin for persistence to HBase (HADOOP) datastores</li>
                <li>Allow query execution in separate thread to allow for cancel/timeout hooks</li>
                <li>Change default for non-transactional read/write to true for JDO</li>
                <li>Support atomic non-transactional write persist/delete operations</li>
                <li>Support for in-memory evaluation of queries with variables</li>
                <li>Support for in-memory evaluation of queries with List.get(), and ranges using parameters</li>
                <li>Drop support for various extensions that were standardised during version 1.1 timeframe</li>
                <li>Split query cache into 3 components : generic compilation, datastore compilation
                    and query results. Added API for managing caching of query results (using JDO or JPA).</li>
                <li>Internal changes to implementation of StoreManager making it even easier to provide
                    support for new datastores</li>
                <li>Bug fix for annotation of unmapped columns in JDO</li>
                <li>Refactor all legacy query classes into own package for removal during 2.0 timeline</li>
                <li>Bug fix to JDO Metadata "index" when unique flag not defined</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to COMPLETE_TABLE inheritance when used with JDOQL2</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Change default auto-start mechanism to "None"</li>
                <li>RDBMS : JDOQL2 support for input params with multiple columns</li>
                <li>RDBMS : JDOQL2 support for List.get()</li>
                <li>RDBMS : JDOQL2 support for range defined with input parameters</li>
                <li>RDBMS : JDOQL2/JPQL2 support for views</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Revised handling of nullability on joins</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Support for table creation with columns having default of NULL</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Support for specifying the order of columns in DDL</li>
                <li>Much internal refactoring has also been performed to remove unneeded components
                    or to simplify the API's for things needed in the 2.0 timeline. Any use of internal
                    API's by applications will likely need changes.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/project/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>