<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 2.0.1 Released">
            <p>
                <b>February 6th 2010</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 2.0.1 is released ("Bohr").
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, and Excel.
                <i>Version 2.0.1</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Support for JPA2 Criteria query API (doesn't yet support subqueries, and some less useful
                   query builder methods)</li>
                <li>Change all primitive wrapper constructor usage to use class valueOf() for efficiency</li>
                <li>Fix to annotation processing to ignore all unsupported class annotations, and to correctly
                    handle methods called get(), is()</li>
                <li>Complete generic compile of JPQL TRIM and LIKE keywords, and support COALESCE, NULLIF keywords</li>
                <li>Add support for in-memory query evaluation of COALESCE/NULLIF keywords</li>
                <li>Update in-memory query evaluator to load fields where needed</li>
                <li>Minor fixes to JDO getObjectById to pass new tests in JDO2.3 TCK</li>
                <li>Minor changes to JDO timeout setter methods to pass new tests in JDO2.3 TCK</li>
                <li>Fix to L2 cache retrieval of relation field to use the value</li>
                <li>Fix to use of @Persistent and @Extension on a field, so that the settings are respected</li>
                <li>Clean up of generic query compilation expressions to not use SymbolTable before bind()</li>
                <li>XML : Fix to handling of empty XML file when searching for an object</li>
                <li>RDBMS : respect "indexed" value of false when creating indexes</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to SQL embed extension so we have SQL_boolean, SQL_numeric static functions</li>
                <li>RDBMS : support for JPQL COALESCE, NULLIF functions</li>
                <li>RDBMS : fix to JPQL to not add dup joins when defined in FROM clause and also from result</li>
                <li>RDBMS : JPQL - support for ESCAPE on LIKE, and support for all TRIM options</li>
                <li>Add support for persisting some java types as Long where no native handling</li>
                <li>HBase : better handling of update to not delete records</li>
                <li>DB4O : upgrade to 7.12 and above</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>