<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 2.2.0 Released">
            <p>
                <b>Dec 10th 2010</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 2.2.0 ("Geiger") is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, and Excel.
                <i>Version 2.2</i> includes the following changes over 2.2 M3
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Fix to threading of transaction manager calls</li>
                <li>Fix to threading of startup of services</li>
                <li>Fix to not L2 cache fields marked as transactional</li>
                <li>Fix to support cascade delete when using "simple" SCO container classes (all datastores except RDBMS)</li>
                <li>Fix to detection of inheritance level of application identity object</li>
                <li>Minor improvement to class loading for querying</li>
                <li>Fix to non-transactional connection retention to clean out connections when closing the PM/EM</li>
                <li>Support for bulk update/delete with JDOQL (DataNucleus extension)</li>
                <li>Fix to deadlock around enlisting of an object in the transaction when updating a field</li>
                <li>Add the ability to define in metadata which classes are pinned in the L2 cache</li>
                <li>Several fixes to L2 caching to make use of relation field information</li>
                <li>JPA : Support for locking</li>
                <li>JPA : Support for fetch groups (DataNucleus extension)</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Merge "datanucleus-connectionpool" into RDBMS plugin</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Provide bundled repackaged DBCP as fallback connection pool</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Support for N-1 uni join table relations</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to nontransactional batched inserts so that all statements are flushed</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Various minor improvements to JDOQL statement generation</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                <i>Version 2.2</i> includes the following major changes over 2.1
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Many improvements to L2 caching</li>
                <li>Various improvements to connection handling for performance</li>
                <li>Improved support for persisting containers with null elements</li>
                <li>JDO : Support for column position specification</li>
                <li>JDO : Support for a typesafe query API</li>
                <li>JPA : More complete JPA2 implementation, providing remaining methods</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Drop legacy JDOQL implementation</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Provide bundled repackaged connection pool (DBCP)</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Support for N-1 uni join table relation</li>
                <li>Other datastores : Support for cascade delete</li>
                <li>Many bug fixes, and minor feature additions.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/project/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>