<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 1.1.4 Released">
            <p>
                <b>June 17th 2009</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 1.1.4 ("Rutherford") is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, Excel, ODF and BigTable.
                <i>Version 1.1.4</i> includes the following changes over 1.1.3
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Make the query cache pluggable, allowing use of external caching products</li>
                <li>Add support for use of Memcache, javax.cache, and EHCache for the query cache</li>
                <li>Addition of upfront checks on whether the datastore supports particular features
                    so allowing quick fail</li>
                <li>Bug fix to datastores which don't provide non-transactional connections</li>
                <li>Simplification of specification of L2 caching, for consistency with L1 cache and
                    Query cache.</li>
                <li>Improvement to classloading for RDBMS "requests" for use in OSGi containers</li>
                <li>Change JPA default for discriminator value to use "class name" when no value specified.</li>
                <li>Improvements to fallback process for persisting a type as a String</li>
                <li>Add control over cascade delete of map keys, and minor change in default</li>
                <li>Bug fix to JPQL "LOWER"/"UPPER" compilation</li>
                <li>Bug fix to List.set() methods when using cascade delete</li>
                <li>Respect JPA "fetch" setting on 1-1 relations</li>
                <li>Support JPA "columnDefinition" in a minimalistic way</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Change fetch process to allow fetching of related (1-1, N-1) objects in same SQL</li>
                <li>RDBSM : Change to Oracle BLOB/CLOB handling to use new SQL API instead of legacy code.</li>
                <li>XML : Bug fix to addition of elements to collection of persistent object</li>
                <li>LDAP : Bug fix to JNDI connection pooling</li>
                <li>LDAP : Support for persisting embedded elements as child entries</li>
                <li>LDAP : Support for inheritance in relationships</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
