<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 2.1.0 Released">
            <p>
                <b>June 11th 2010</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 2.1.0 ("Thomson") is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, and Excel.
                <i>Version 2.1</i> includes the following changes over 2.1 M3
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Changed to use JDO3 jar</li>
                <li>Support for persistence to GoogleStorage</li>
                <li>Support for persistence of some Google Collections classes</li>
                <li>Added initial version of a generic query optimiser, removing redundant variable clauses</li>
                <li>Fix to JPA inheritance strategy "JOINED" when having subclasses with discriminator</li>
                <li>Fix to persist of new object with collection that contains detached objects</li>
                <li>Fix to persist of new object with related detached compound identity chain</li>
                <li>Optimise out some SCO collection operations such as add+delete of same object in succession</li>
                <li>Support persist of enums as arbitrary value</li>
                <li>JPA2 : Support for orphan removal</li>
                <li>JPA2 : Support for JPQL "INDEX" keyword</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to setting of BLOB/CLOB on bidirectional relations for Oracle</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Fix to SQL table namer to allow for unioned statements when choosing table name</li>
                <li>RDBMS : Support for use of BoneCP connection pools</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                <i>Version 2.1</i> includes the following major changes over 2.0
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Support for persistence to OOXML files</li>
                <li>Support for persistence to GoogleStorage</li>
                <li>Support for persistence for fields of some javax.time types</li>
                <li>Support for persistence for fields of some Google Collection types</li>
                <li>Changed to use rewritten JDOQL implementation for RDBMS by default. This makes many more 
                    JDOQL statements runnable than were previously possible</li>
                <li>Uses JDO3 "final" jar</li>
                <li>Uses JPA2 "final" jar</li>
                <li>Supports full JPA2 definition of JPQL</li>
                <li>Supports JPA2 static metamodel creation</li>
                <li>Supports JPA2 orphan removal</li>
                <li>Support for embedded PC objects with Excel persistence</li>
                <li>Support for using spatial methods in queries with the new JDOQL implementation for RDBMS</li>
                <li>Support for BoneCP RDBMS connection pooling library</li>
                <li>Many bug fixes, and minor feature additions.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>