<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <title>News</title>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="DataNucleus Access Platform 1.0 M4 Released">
            <p>
                <b>Auguest 4th 2008</b>- DataNucleus Access Platform 1.0 ("Faraday") Milestone 4 is released.
                DataNucleus Access Platform provides persistence and retrieval of Java objects to/from
                a wide range of datastores including RDBMS, db4o, LDAP, XML, Excel, NeoDatis ODB, and JSON.
                <i>Version 1.0 Milestone 4</i> includes the following changes
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Upgrade to JDO 2.2 (snapshot), NeoDatis 1.9-beta-3, Apache POI 3.1</li>
                <li>Added cache for compiled queries for XML, db4o, Excel, NeoDatis, JSON and LDAP</li>
                <li>Added support for NeoDatis embedded server</li>
                <li>Added full support for JPQL query compilation using generic compiler</li>
                <li>Added support for in-memory JPQL query evaluation of all spec required functions.</li>
                <li>Added support for in-memory JDOQL query evaluation of all spec required methods, with
                    the exception of Collection.contains, Map.containsKey, Map.containsValue, Map.get</li>
                <li>Support for JDO2.2 @Cacheable allowing control over classes/fields to be cached</li>
                <li>Added pluggable support for generic query methods/functions</li>
                <li>Added support for use of implicit/explicit parameters with generic JDOQL/JPQL</li>
                <li>Added support for use of DISTINCT with generic JDOQL/JPQL</li>
                <li>Expanded the support for in-memory evaluation of aggregates to cater for all types of 
                    fields</li>
                <li>Bug fix to runtime bytecode enhancement allowing its use with annotated classes, and
                    added optimisation to specify the packages to be runtime enhanced providing big speedups</li>
                <li>Fixes to allow complete use of Access Platform in a java security environment</li>
                <li>Support for JPA2 @ElementCollection/@CollectionTable</li>
                <li>Support for performing db4o/NeoDatis JDOQL/JPQL queries totally in-memory where required</li>
                <li>Bug fix to allow use of RDBMS datastores that store in lowercase without the need to
                    provide a persistence property to specify this</li>
                <li>Bug fix to RDBMS persistence of complicated hierarchy with container+inheritance
                    and multiple relations between container and element, avoiding FK violation</li>
                <li>Bug fix to L2 caching for multithreaded operations</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                This release is downloadable under an Apache 2 license from the
                <a href="http://www.datanucleus.org/project/download.html">DataNucleus community site</a>.
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>